[Music]
foreign
welcome to the 136th episode of the ask
of the show
so before we get into the questions
which are going to be from the live chat
today let us see who all is there with
us and I'm sure lots of interesting
things are happening worldwide that we
could talk about so let us see who all
is there I can see Suraj knowledge with
anadi Vivek tanai Rita adesh darshan
foreign
[Music]
and a lot of people thank you all for
being on the show with us and let us get
into the questions
so what questions do we have for today
what questions do we have let us see
what questions we have uh let's see
start asking your questions and I'll
pick as many as I can
so uh I think we should start where we
should start
smart money asks is Sri Jinping really
under house arrest
yeah I mean I don't know what's
happening in China you know there are
these rumors swirling around on social
media mostly on social media some on
YouTube Etc rumors about Shri gymping
having disappeared he is no longer
visible uh there was some big meeting or
convention or something in which he uh
did not appear but he gave a recorded
pre-recorded message that somebody else
read out for him that sort of thing uh
the situation in Beijing is weird all
the flights are being canceled thousands
of flights have been canceled let's take
a look at what uh
what the situation in Beijing is like
Flight Radar 24
.com let's see that
one second let me put that on the screen
and let's see what Beijing looks like
right now what's happening in Beijing
uh here we are here we are come on all
right this is Flight Radar 24 let's go
into China which is east of India
Beijing is the northeast of China
so where is Beijing ah Beijing check it
out Beijing is typically the busiest
airport in China
and if you look here there's nothing
happening
there's nothing happening in Beijing
where are the planes where are the
aircraft
very few flights around Beijing and the
entire airspace seems to have been
cleared out which is extremely strange I
hear that thousands of trains have been
canceled yes there are definitely planes
going around taking off and coming down
uh in other parts of China but Beijing
suspiciously very clear so there is
clearly some sort of abnormal situation
in China
and it it appears that Mr uh Xi Jinping
uh rushed back to to China to Beijing
from the SEO Summit where he
participated in uh Samarkand Uzbekistan
I think where Mr Modi was there Mr Putin
was there in various other uh leaders of
the sea over there so Mr
Xi Jinping rushed back to China
apparently and after that he has not
been seen that's what one hears and
there is no official confirmation or
denial from the various Chinese uh news
outlets media Outlets from their various
officials nothing they are quite about
this tight-lipped
and uh there is no actual proof as of
today that something has happened maybe
who has happened but there is nothing
that proves that a coup hasn't happened
either
you know so we are kind of in limbo we
don't have a confirmation either for or
against a coup now I have uh
spoken about this various times uh in
the past year or year or so on this
channel that Aku is always on the cards
when it comes to China China is a
one-party dictatorship right and there's
no democracy within the Communist party
and in China
it's typically the strongest and most
powerful leader who makes his way to the
top typically it's a he yeah it's now
been a she it's it's the most brutal the
most Cutthroat leader who makes his way
to the top and
the leader will continue as long as he
or she as long as he typically uh serves
the agenda of the Chinese Communist
Party of enriching the party and taking
the nation forward in the right
direction which they which they want and
so on
and they obviously would not want the
leader to become too powerful yeah and
there is a hierarchy in the Chinese
Communist Party a power structure these
the core leadership is called the
politic Bureau of the Chinese Communist
Party of the CCP which is a bunch a
small number of very powerful
individuals the most powerful
individuals in China and out of that
group that Core group one leader is
typically chosen it's not an election
it's a selection and Mr Xi Jinping has
been around for 10 years now typically a
leader is chosen for five years now he's
been around for 10 years and this uh by
the end of the year maybe in October he
was supposed to be re-selected for
another five-year term right so
um
he obviously has lots of enemies within
the Chinese Communist Party the Chinese
political system is a one-party system
it's extremely competitive it's a dog
eat dog world you rise to the top you
gotta make thousands of enemies Mr Xi
Jinping has left lots of political
opponents in his wake many of them have
been imprisoned for corruption or
whatever and so on he's made lots of
enemies but he as long as he has the
control of The reigns of power he is
Untouchable but
there will be sections in the Chinese
Communist Party who resent uh what he
has done and who will be envious of his
position and who would seek to replace
him and that's a constant power struggle
that goes on in any organization whether
it's uh dictatorial or Democratic or
whatever we see this everywhere but in
China it's expensive especially
accentuated
so what is the deal well as of today as
of right now what is the date today
today is the the what is the date uh
today is the 24th of September 2022. as
of today we don't know what the
situation is the situation seems to be
very unnamed very ambiguous we don't
know yeah it looks like there could be
something going on I just showed you
what's happening in Beijing all the
flights have been canceled that is
extremely weird
Beijing is the one of the busiest
airports in the entire world look at
this
it's like crickets nothing happening
here which is extremely unusual I cannot
remember the last last time something
like this happened in Beijing and not
only the airport thousands of play of
trains have been canceled especially in
the Beijing area and all that so clearly
something unusual happening now we don't
know what it is it's not I mean in the
past the Chinese have shut down the
country at various points in time in
various cities like uh Shanghai for
instance and even Beijing and other
places because of the kovid outbreak
right the covet pandemic and because of
because they have this very strict no
covet policy they would typically uh
shut down a city or an entire Province
for a month two months who knows how
long and so during the past two years
various such things have happened but
this doesn't look like it's covered
that's that's appeared uh suddenly out
of nowhere overnight that doesn't make
sense so clearly something is happening
and Mr Xi Jinping has not been seen in
public since the SEO Summit since he
rushed back home after the SEO Summit so
what is the possible what are the
possibilities what could have gone what
could have happened first maybe there's
a coup
second maybe there's some new viruses
come out and everybody is scampering for
cover third
maybe he's unwell that's also a
possibility Mr Xi Jinping isn't the
healthiest person even when he was first
appointed as the uh leader of China 10
years ago he disappeared for a month or
two to take care of some health issues
yeah
so yeah if you look at him he's not the
slimmest person he's kind of overweight
and he may have health issues there's no
he's not the youngest person either he's
most likely in his late 60s early 70s
somewhere around there most likely late
60s yeah so there could be a
possibly several reasons why uh Mr XI
jinpick has disappeared but that if he
has health issues that doesn't account
for the closure of the airspace around
Beijing yeah and some media Outlets are
saying that maybe uh the Chinese
military is conducting some exercises
and that's why they have closed on the
airspace well it doesn't quite add up
yeah and if they are really closing of
the airspace for military purposes then
it's it's alarm Bells all around China
you know if the Chinese are closing down
significant portions of the airspace for
whatever they're doing so yeah as of
today we don't know what's happening but
clearly something strange is happening
in China and let's see let's see what
happens we'll have to keep an eye on
this tomorrow I will revisit this topic
again hopefully with hopefully with some
new information which will hopefully
give us some clarity but that's where we
are right now I have a couple of videos
on this channel one or two by myself
about why a coup is always on the cards
in China look it up search it on my
channel Aku is always of the cars in
China and is another video with from the
podcast between with me and Dr Edward
Luther who's a one of the great Geo
strategist so alive today so in that
video he has he explains how a coup
would happen possibly against Mr Xi
Jinping you know so if you're interested
do check out those videos
all right let's see what else we have
what else do we have
that's what I'm talking about my dear
friends that's what I'm talking about I
just spoke about it now
um
Rishi says why do you think zelinski
from Ukraine backed India's permanent
UNSC membership bid even when India
didn't condemn Russia
I I'm not aware of what Mr zilinski had
said or not said but you know what we
are talking about here we're talking
about a statement what is a statement
it's words words make no difference
people Indians are so enamored with
words he said this he has supported us
he has supported nothing a statement is
like a feather in the wind the wind will
blow the feather will disappear you'll
never see it again statements in words
are ephemeral they mean nothing if they
truly if zelinski truly wants to back
India's claim then he should Lobby
support with the with his bosses in the
United States right and other nations of
a statement makes no difference it
changes nothing in the world I can make
50 statements today and turn three
months from now nobody will remember
that yeah any and politicians they make
statements all the time they make
statements on the record and then they
contracted themselves a week later and
they don't care about that yeah so these
statements mean nothing the only thing
that matters is actual actions and we
see no actions about this you see the
Americans saying from time to time that
they support India's bid for whatever
permanent Union UNSC membership have
they done a single thing about that have
they taken a single step in that
direction about opening up the
possibility
for India's membership permanent
membership in the UNSC no they've done
nothing words words please stop
getting being enamored with words words
mean nothing words are the currency of
the politicians and in geopolitics you
can say anything you want but at the end
of the day what you do what your actions
are that's the only thing that matters
and so this is pointless it is it is
Irrelevant in the uh geopolitical
context
all right
Vanoss says why didn't the British
colonize Nepal when the whereas they
managed to capture the entire
subcontinent of India was there any
specific reason for that the British
even launched an expedition into Tibet
in in which they are kind of um
um brought Tibet to a certain extent
under their uh not exactly control but
they impose certain conditions trade
conditions Etc on Tibet and they opened
up Tibet to Future exploration by them
in the context of the great game that
was being played geopolitically between
the the British Empire the Russians the
Turks and so on so forth for control of
Central Asia yeah uh
so why didn't the British colonize Nepal
you know the Nepalese were only in name
not colonized of course the British did
not see first of all Nepal as you know
is a mountainous hilly region there is a
tarai region in the South and then
there's the mountainous Hill region in
the north and that's where Kathmandu is
ensconced right Kathmandu the capital
city there's not much of value that sits
in Nepal Nepal isn't a resource Rich
region it doesn't produce much yeah
Nepal has always been an extension of
the Indian subcontinent it's part of the
Indian subcontinent it's always been
part of various Indian Empires and
kingdoms yeah and there's nothing much
specifically that grows there so the
British decided to use Nepal as a buffer
State between
British India and Tibet where there was
there were these Chinese claims you know
the Chinese were claiming uh the Chinese
were interfering in Tibet and there was
a possibility of a confrontation of some
kind between the British Raj and the
Chinese Empire from time to time so they
wanted to keep us a region is a buffer
State and they chose Nepal for that and
yet you see that the Nepal were great at
The Nepalese were greatly dependent on
the British for a variety of things for
instance the entire practice of sending
uh Gurkha soldiers to the British army
began during this period yeah even today
various uh
Gurkha soldiers still serve in the in
the British armed forces and they're not
treated quite well right they don't get
the Kaya Saint pensions as the British
guys get and all that so and yet it's
it's a step forward for them it's it's
uh an opportunity for a good future so
the British uh and and if you recall if
you recall the incident in jallianwala
bhag uh the soldiers who fired at the uh
the the
innocent people men women children ninja
half of them were either Balochi or
pashtoon and half of them were gurkhas
right so that tells you the whole story
I mean that tells you a significant
amount that you need to understand that
Nepal May technically not have been
under British rule the British may not
have had a political agent in Nepal the
British may not have collected taxes
from Nepal and yet Nepal was essentially
entirely at the mercy of the British Raj
if the Nepalese monarchy did not you
know a fall in line with all the demands
of the British then there would have
been a next anytime the British were in
a position to Annex Nepal anytime they
wanted but they did not choose to do
that they chose not to do that in order
to not get embroiled in any situation or
scenario with China when China was
making claims to Tibet and there was all
this thing happening so that's what they
wanted to do and that's why uh it was
not officially a next or colonized
yeah
right what other questions do we have uh
what do you think of Iranian women
burning burkas well it's entirely up to
the Iranian ladies what they want to do
and the people of Iran I think the
people should have a choice in whatever
they want to do but they want to wear
something they don't want to wear
something I think it's their business
it's their internal matter uh we should
not get excited about anything that's
happening there it's not our business uh
the entire geopolitical thing is you
know world affairs in international
Affairs is predicated on the principle
of non-interference
so as far as as long as Iran doesn't
interfere in India's internal matters we
should not interfere in their matters
whatever is happening there is for them
to decide the people and the government
if there is a clash between the people
in the government well one will come out
on top and that's how it goes at the end
of the day it's about power and control
so uh what do I think of the Iranian
women doing this well it is their choice
and uh let the people of Iran decide
what they want in the long run that's
what I would say
all right YouTube account says has
Communism ever been implemented in the
exact way of Karl Marx how could that
Society be like well if you look at what
Karl Marx wrote he wrote a voluminous uh
volumes one is the uh what is it called
the Communist manufacture Manifesto the
second one is uh Das Capital right is a
massively enormous book I don't think
anybody reads that but it's there you
know so the thicker the book you write
the more imminent you become as and and
now he's considered to be philosopher so
what kind of Communism did he envisage
Karl Marx envisaged that a Boudoir
capitalist Society should be destroyed
via a Communist Revolution
right a revolution led by the
proletariat which is the working classes
so he wanted the workers to unite and
and overthrow the rulers the capitalists
in the Bourgeois means those who who
benefit from from capitalism
and
so he wanted a Communist Revolution in
any Bourgeois capitalist Society after
that he did not say anything about what
kind of society should exist after the
so-called Revolution supposedly succeeds
so here's the problem with Marxism when
you Advocate a revolution you are
advocating violence you're advocating
mobs and Rampages of the streets by the
workers right you're advocating violence
a violent overthrow of the existing
government that's what you're advocating
now Karl Marx did not specify what sort
of leadership
this revolution should have what kind of
people should be the leaders of such a
Communist Revolution
yeah he did not say whether such leaders
should be elected they should be
appointed or just some thugs should get
together and the biggest thug should
rule typically in a violent revolution
it's the most violent elements of
society that come together and come to
the top as the leaders the the more
brutal and more violent you are the
higher you rise in a violent Society
that's how it works so when you Advocate
a revolution that is a violent overthrow
of the government you're typically gonna
have the most brutal and most violent
people rising to the top the most
ruthless people and that's what you see
all the time in any communist Society in
the past you've seen that right
so Mr Karl Marx did not specify what
sort of leadership he wanted to lead the
Communist Revolution the revolution of
the proletariat and then he said that he
wanted the post-revolution society to be
a dictatorship of the proletariat which
means a core government that will rule
the entire country on behalf of the
workers now who will elect this
government and its leaders will it be a
democratic election or will these will
the tough and and violent and brutal
guys who let the revolution will they
lead this as the dictators so he did not
specify any of these things and that's
where there is so much ambiguity and
that's why there are so many problems
with communism because it's always the
most brutal people who rise to the top
look at the Chinese Communist Party
I mean they did succeed in uh in
evicting the kovindang and and uh and
defeating the Japanese and uh taking
over the country but look at the
incredible brutality the Chinese
Communist Party perpetrated on the
people of China in the 20th century
close to 100 million people must have
died in in the various uh excesses that
they perpeted the Great Leap Forward
uh the the I don't know what all they
did right I don't remember exactly but
the biggest culprit was Mao Zedong crazy
guy absolutely crazy guy but he is
revered and loved by many Chinese even
today and they say that what he did was
right he cleansed the Society of the of
the of the bad elements yeah well 100
million people that's how bad your
Society was I don't know what the number
is some say 40 million some say 80
billion some say 100 million whatever it
is even a million is is incredibly
ridiculous
and you say the same thing in other
places look at the USSR look at this
stalinist brutality in the USR look at
what it did in in novorossia in Ukraine
the whole of the more the deliberate
starvation of the people and all the
other things that happened in
stalinistration millions of people died
during that phase as well and even later
the system was extremely oppressive
wasn't it right uh Collective forced
collectivization no right to property
and uh you know the the in the KGB was
everywhere eyes and ears everywhere you
did not know who was who was your friend
who was your enemy even your family
could be somebody who could have their
who would betray you you saw the same
thing in East Germany the Stasi yes the
secret police that would spy upon the
people and so on and so forth so
that's the problem with Communism Karl
Marx did not specify clearly what sort
of society he wanted in the
post-revolution era when the Communists
take power he specified nothing and
that's why it's always been this way
right he was not clear about what he was
uh prescribing for society and that's
the biggest problem he he created he he
called for a revolution he called for
violence he called for these overthrows
he said he wants the dictatorship of the
proletariat and he created this
wonderful pseudo-intellectual framework
with these fantastic words like
prolitarian and bourgeoisie and and the
lumpin elements and the lump and
proletariat it sounds so intellectual it
sounds so intelligent when you absorb
Karl Marx's terminology you start giving
speeches with that people think that you
got everything figured out you don't
want to you understand everything
and it's typically the most brutal
people who are drawn to the Communist
ideology because it serves them
and 99 of people who espouse communism
are the current father the people in the
streets they will benefit not at all
from it it's only a very small
percentage of the population that
ends up benefiting the most they end up
hoarding a hundred percent of the power
and 100 of the wealth of the entire
nation and they rule as a dictatorship
of the proletariat that is the problem
with Communism so that's why uh because
so communism has never been implemented
in the exact way of Karl Marx because he
did not specify any exact way at all
that's the problem with him
uh um yoga says how do we stop drain of
brain well you need to make the country
better we need to have better education
system you need to have meritocracy in
the nation see the problem is that there
is no meritocracy in India in government
jobs you have all the reservations in in
the education system in universities and
colleges you have these massive amounts
of reservations and uh there is so much
corruption there is so much
misgovernance the roads are bad the
traffic is always congested cities
whenever it rains they go underwater
from time to time especially even even
large cities and there are so many
problems if you have a society that is
structured in this manner where all the
institutions are still Colonial in
nature where the institutions do not
serve carry out the functions that they
are supposed to carry out when you have
a nation that is built like this then
people are going to try and leave for
better prospects they may love the
nation and the culture and the
civilization but they will go out of the
country for the sake of themselves
they're a better life and for the sake
of the children and that's why Indians
have been leaving India from for
Generations typically to
English-speaking Nations typically the
U.S or or the UK nowadays even to
Australia some Indians are going to
other countries as well
maybe in Europe or whatever so that is
the cause of brain drain right so you
need to restructure the country I mean
reform all the various uh institutions
in the country the education system you
need to make India completely
meritocratic country everybody should
get enough opportunities multiple
opportunities you know once you take a
job you should not have the job for life
you should have multiple options you
should be able to change careers
whatever time you want yeah so you need
to offer people multiple opportunities
and you need to offer people the
possibility
to rise to the highest of their
potential any nation that offers this is
going to be very attractive not only to
its own citizens but to Outsiders as
well and typically for the longest time
it's been the US that has offered this
the US is
a fully capitalist Nation there are
people in the U.S who have to struggle
to even put food on the table they do
two jobs three dogs three jobs in a day
they sleep four hours five hours a day
and even after working so much they are
able to only barely put food on the
table for their families right it's the
people who don't have any skills in
education but if you are educated if you
have skills then the sky is the limit
for you in the U.S so typically Indians
who go there are very highly educated
and that's why anybody who acquires a
master's level education you know
University level education wants to
immigrate to the US U.S because of all
this because in the U.S as long as you
keep your culture you know you subdue
your culture don't don't uh
show any pride in your culture and as
long as you assimilate and you work hard
you can rise very high and you see all
kinds of various American companies have
Indian CEOs a whole bunch of major
American corporations have Indian CEOs
right so India and you have many
companies in Silicon Valley that have
been founded by Indians and so on Indian
origin people so you give people the
opportunity to rise to the uh to the
fullest of their potential they will
find that attractive so India needs to
do that India needs to find ways of do
that there are so many issues in India
transportation is bad the infrastructure
is bad the roads are bad there is no
rule of law in order and some people get
upset when I say there's no rule of law
go outside your house and start in the
street do you see anybody following
traffic rules do you see any government
official enforcing traffic rules there
you go there is no rule of law
yeah
so there are all these issues you fix
the issues India will again become
attractive for not only Indians for but
even for Outsiders you rise to a certain
level of greatness people will stop
leaving
so how do you stop brain brain drain by
making India great again it's a cliched
phrase but that's the deal India always
has been the greatest civilization the
most prosperous civilization you go back
on track with that everybody is going to
come back even those who have left India
10 20 years ago for better prospects in
other nations they will be highly
tempted to come back and you give enough
opportunities everybody will come back
so that's what needs to happen right
that's what needs to happen
all right all right all right some some
what other questions
um
what did people eat during the Rama and
era well we don't have any textual
evidence of what people used to eat we
do have some stories from the Rama and
that Lord Rama was eating those berries
bear you know that lady offered in
shabari and so on
um so I don't we don't have any actual
evidence of what people used to eat or
not eat yes India is a massive massive
massive place it's an enormous
subcontinent sized region in case you're
not aware let me show you
here look at the maps here's the map
where's the map come on map here we are
see how large India is enormous I mean
we Indians are used to seeing this thing
and it looks very small but you can fit
France and Germany and Spain and the UK
and I'm sure a little bit more inside
the Indian subcontinent and still have
room to spare it's enormous so what did
people eat people would have eaten
different kinds of diets at different
parts of in different parts of India
right so when you talk about ayodhya it
was part of the coastal mahajanapada and
then you have Lanka which is down south
and so on so I would say I would imagine
that in different parts of the
subcontinent people would have eaten
different kinds of food
what do we have any idea for sure what
they used to eat I am not sure because
there is no textual evidence or record
left today surviving today that uh maybe
provides maybe a cookbook from the time
what recipes did Indians have we don't
have any of that so we can only
speculate right but I would imagine in
Indians of of that time would have eaten
pretty much what Indians eat today apart
from all the foreign inflows that have
crept in yes
so that's what I could say that's what I
would be able to tell you now let's see
if do we have other questions that are
more interesting
aha now world war three
listen it's it's fun to think of Wars
but it's not fun Wars are terrible
um Wars are never good
Wars sometimes are necessary for Nations
to uh
in order to achieve Justice or whatever
they seek but the ones who suffer in
Wars are always the innocent men women
in children the innocent citizens so uh
we should not uh be very excited about
this Prospect now is world war three on
the in the offing is it on the cards
world war three I hope is not on the
cards uh what could set of World War III
of world war three kind of situation is
typically when you have a complete
bifurcation of the global system and you
have one massive power
one major power that is trying to
replace another major power that's
typically the the China U.S paradigm
the U.S is still enormously more
powerful than China their military uh
industrial complex it's it dwarves
anything China has right the Chinese are
trying to rise they are trying to rise
but they are still no match for the U.S
they can't even dig back China uh take
back Taiwan as of 2022. maybe in the
next five to seven years they may
possibly feel that they are right
they're there and they can do it at the
time but right now they're not even a
position to take back Taiwan so so so
right now I don't see I still don't see
uh world war three happening anytime in
the immediate future there is the
Ukraine conflagration that's happening
yeah the Ukraine war is happening I
don't know what's happening you have all
kinds of reports coming in in the
western media it's typically that Russia
is losing Ukraine is winning that's what
they've been saying since February well
let's let's keep an eye on that I
typically
uh see the situation on a month-to-month
basis because day to day if you look at
it you will get misled by what the
propaganda that's flowing around tells
you so you have the Ukraine law the
Ukraine conflict the West is not getting
involved directly they are using proxies
they are sending arms and ammunition to
Ukraine to fight the Russians so it's
essentially
uh that war is between Russia and the
West especially essentially Russia and
the U.S with the ukrainians fighting on
behalf of the Americans and the
Americans will fight Russia to the last
Ukrainian so that award is going it
looks like it's going to go on unless
there is a ceasefire and something
something like that which will happen
only when Russia has achieved whatever
objectives it wanted to achieve so the
Russians will not stop until that uh
those objectives are achieved
so you have the Ukraine flash point and
apart from that there is no other hot
War happening and as long as nobody
makes any silly silly moves World War
III will most likely not happen we have
to understand what the red lines are
what are China's Redlands what are
Russia's red lines what are America's
red lines what are India's red lines and
so on once you understand that you can
understand what can trigger a war
so what are China's red lines I think
too much of you U.S encroachment in
various uh parts
territorial religions that the Chinese
see as their own especially Taiwan if
there are too many provocations
vis-a-vis Taiwan there could be
something happening there
uh Japan and China also have a dispute
there are problems there so there are
many flash points geopolitical flash
points across the world which we can see
on the map but as of now I do not see
World War III starting off anytime soon
and I hope it never happens Wars will
happen Wars are something that have
always happened it's it's how things are
done that's how we humans roll we are a
species of Warriors we we resolve our
differences in the long run with through
wars only so Wars will come and go but
hopefully nothing major and so yeah as
of now I don't see world war three
erupting in a time zone
right uh what else do we have
a smoothie says if SRI Jinping gets
removed will there be a change in
approach towards India if relations
between India and China improve do both
together have the potential to undermine
U.S in the world
so there is always this hope that I see
from Indians of uh some kind of India
China rapprochemo in India China will
form an alliance
and
work against the West
I don't see that happening see if you
look see it's not about Mr Xi Jinping or
anybody else it's about the overall
policy of the Chinese Communist Party
from 90 from 1949 or whenever it was
that they came to power until 2022 what
has the official policy
of the Chinese Communist Party been not
through words but what are the what have
their actions been like they have always
been hostile towards India whether it
was the time during the time of Mao
zatong and during the time when uh Lai
was the uh foreign minister whatever or
whatever he was
or later during the time of Deng
Xiaoping when again there was a small
border war between India and China 1987
yeah which nobody remembers
then there were two Wars earlier 1962
which India lost 1967 that India won and
even in the 2000s the Chinese started
making claims on arunachal Pradesh so
it's not about a particular individual
it's about the Chinese Communist party
and how they see India the Chinese
Communist Party sees India as a
potential long-term threat if India
Rises they will
feel they feel that it will be a big
threat towards China because China holds
so many territories that don't belong to
them they hold Tibet Tibet has always
been part of the Indo sphere
Tibet was India's part of India's
extended sphere of influence in India's
extended cultural sphere they hold that
and as long as the Chinese hold Tibet
India and China are always going to have
friction and tensions which may lead to
Wars
so the key to the issue is Tibet it's
not the demarcation of the India China
border which of course the Chinese again
they don't want even that to happen so
if India Rises it's going to be a threat
to China they know it and I think you
also know it
if India becomes a 10 trillion dollar
economy with a massive military do you
not think India would want to take back
Tibet at least free Tibet from China of
course it is that is the solution to all
the problems so
no matter who comes to power let's say
Mr Xi Jinping gets removed and some
other person comes to power it will make
no difference in China's approach
towards India China will always be an
adversary to India as long as the whole
territory that doesn't belong to them
that has historically never been theirs
Tibet as long as that happens China and
India are going to have this adversarial
enemy relationship relations between
India and China can improve only if
India Rises
right so paradoxically the key to good
relations reasonably good relations is
India's rise as long as India is
a middle power a small power like a 3.6
trillion dollar economy which is not
small but it's not big either India is a
middle power right now India is a future
great power everyone now recognizes this
right so the Chinese don't want that
future future to ever happen they don't
want India to become a great power but
if India does become a great power then
it will become too strong for the
Chinese to ever
think about attacking and then they will
be able they will be forced to make
certain compromises and there will be a
forced piece of sorts so though that is
not good relations that is China
recognizing the fact that they cannot
now afford to antagonize India too much
and then there will be a cool piece kind
of thing it will never be warm relations
like we had for 2000 years right China
is two thousand three thousand years old
whatever so we had good relations
between India and China for 2000 years
ever since the the Chinese discovered
Indian culture through the works of
first the mauryan Empire then the kushan
empire under kanishka the great and so
on
so India and China always had great
relations but now that they have
captured Tibet that doesn't belong to
them they now covet more territory you
know they want to keep on nibbling
awaiting in territory and keep India off
balance keep India always discomfited
that is a policy that's their official
line or an official line unstated line
that's what they've always done the
salami slicing and nibbling away at
small pieces of territory they keep
doing that and they don't want to uh
demarcate the border for that reason so
the only solution is for India to rise
to a minimum 10 trillion dollar economy
in the next 10 15 years the Chinese will
do their best not not to let that happen
but India has to make that happen then
there will be a cold peace between India
and China
the Chinese will see India as an even
bigger threat but they will not able to
be to do do anything about that the way
they are able to do right now to some
extent so that's what's happening so
relations within India and China will
not improve as long as the Chinese
Communist Party holds Tibet the solution
to the entire problem is Tibet India has
to somehow one way or the other engineer
The Liberation of Tibet and the complete
uh
deletion of any Chinese influence there
and that's going to take some taking
take some doing yeah so uh
so uh is there a possibility for India
China Alliance no not as long as the
Chinese Communist Party holds Tibet and
mostly most likely not as whole long as
the Chinese Communist Party remains in
power
so India and China are not going to work
together they are always going to have
an adversary relationship there could be
some times in the future possibly some
kind of uh
some kind of agreement of convenience or
whatever but that is not going to last
long this is exactly the same way Russia
and China right now are working together
but they are long-term enemies Russia
and China are long-term enemies they are
not going to be on good terms in the
long-term future maybe 10 years 20 years
and then the old rivalries and issues
will re-emerge right so similarly in the
future there could be some temporary uh
understanding between India and China
but it's not going to be a long-term
thing yeah so India essentially doesn't
have any real allies whatever
relationship India has with Russia is a
relationship of good understanding of
warm there have been historically good
ties and Russia obviously would like to
see India rise vis-a-vis China so that's
where we are today
and if you want to undermine the U.S I
don't want to undermine anybody I just
want India to rise that's all it doesn't
have to be at somebody else's expense we
can have a multi-polar world
for now for for some time and then we'll
see
all right
okay let's uh see then see some other
comments what do we have
um
opinion on Bollywood planning a movie on
the Mahabharata
ah
I don't have a good feeling about it
yeah Bollywood planning anything on
Indian culture is going to distort
Indian culture I wonder who the old
actors they will see they they only have
a few actors and actresses that they
typically employ for any major role so
it's going to be some 60 year old actor
who's gonna play the role of the young
Lord Rama and the young Lord rakshman
lakshman and Bharat and so on
and you know the casting
as far as I see from their track record
I can say that the casting will be bad
and they will distort Indian history and
culture so if the movie is made or
whatever I am certainly not going to go
and watch it I'm not going to waste my
time and money yeah I would really like
to see a long series about the ramayan
and the Mahabharata being made the kind
of production that you have in the Game
of Thrones or the house of the Dragon
really well made 10 episodes per season
maybe three Seasons Four Seasons you
know so 30 40 episodes maybe 50 episodes
one hour long that would do justice to
something as complicated and as as as as
culturally deep and historically vast as
the ramayan or the Mahabharata or you
could do it through animation the
Japanese I believe had done a very good
animation like 20 30 years ago about
either the ramayan or the mother maybe
the ramayan I would like to see this
done but it should do justice to the
events that happen not some stupid
bollywood-ized version that I certainly
will not watch so that's my opinion
about this it's not some great news or
anything I'm certainly not watching uh
most likely they will put some
I don't know who they'll put in the
titular rules but yeah are interesting
not interested
all right
why is the us at war with Russia when it
is clear that China is the greatest
threat enemy right now no Russia is you
don't understand how see
yeah China is uh economically
the biggest threat right now to the U.S
the Chinese seek to undermine the
so-called whims-based Global Order that
the Americans have created and the
entire economic framework that they've
created they seek to seek to bifurcate
the system the global system so a bunch
of countries in China's side a bunch of
countries in the U.S side and then let's
see who wins that sort of thing the
Chinese seek to do that
but understand what Russia is Russia is
at number 10 in the top 10 economies
maybe number 11 but if you look at the
real
the real GDP the Russians are number two
number three
if you look at the factors in the GDP
that really matter
whether it comes to agricultural output
or or mineral output or energy output or
steel output if you consider only these
core factors
in a nation's GDP then Russia is at
number two or number three all the other
factors like goods and services and all
that stuff that that is fluff you know
that's how you inflate a GDP so the real
core component of what goes into
calculating a GDP if you only consider
that Russia is at number two or number
three that's why they are able to
withstand all the sanctions that the US
is throwing at them it makes no
difference to them they are
self-sufficient in energy nobody can
stop them from uh from they have more
than sufficient reserves of gas and coal
and hydrocarbons and oil they don't need
it from anybody else again they have all
the industries they they make money they
have steel or steel mines gold mines and
they have enormous amounts of
agricultural land so all the
fundamentals are covered right there so
they are completely self-sufficient they
are in otaki completely self-sufficient
uh Nation
and they are a very strong economy
secondly
secondly they have the world's largest
nuclear Arsenal
the Russians have a bigger nuclear
Arsenal than the Americans and the
Chinese don't even figure in this this
comparison
so the Russians are possibly the
greatest military power of course they
don't have the kind of network of Global
Network of military bases like the
Americans have in Japan in Germany all
across Europe in Turkey in Belgium in
the Netherlands in Italy in the Indian
Ocean region you know Diego Garcia in
Australia Australia is essentially owned
by the US it's like a U.S corporation
and so on the Americans have a network
of Base everywhere military bases
permanent basis more or less the
Russians don't have that
but they have a very strong military
they have the means to deploy weapons
and Warheads anywhere they want so
Russia is actually in some ways a bigger
threat than China right and the
Americans tried to destroy Russia in the
in the 1990s why are Boris Yeltsin Boris
Johnson essentially did his best to just
to deliberately and systematically and
step by step destroy Russia's economy he
succeeded to a large extent but then
something inconvenient happened Vladimir
Putin came to power and he rebuilt the
economy over a period of about 10-15
years and then the military again became
became powerful because the economy
stopped crumbling
and today Russia is again a force to be
reckoned with it's no longer a global
superpower like it was
30 40 years ago or it's still one of the
major powers and it's a huge threat to
the U.S so we've got to understand this
to to to understand why the U.S still is
trying their best to undermine the
Russians in a variety of ways
okay
grantman says can anyone conduct an
ashwamedayagna or do you have to be a
king to do one I do want to claim
control of the universe just a power
hungry medical student here
typically done by Kings okay so what the
king would do is that king would uh
perform a ritual you know according to
the proper Vedic traditions in which a
horse would be set free to roam and
wander wherever he wanted
and
it was I think the time period was one
year so the horse would wander and roam
anywhere he wanted for one year and any
king or other territory that the horse
wandered into
that local king would have two choices
either resist
the and in the horse wherever he wanders
would be accompanied by Soldiers by
essentially battalions and Detachment of
an army so if the horse wandered into a
neighbor's territory then the
neighboring king would have two choices
either resist the the incursion of the
of the horse and the Army through
Warfare or accept the superiority of the
king who is conducting that
so either war or you become a vasal
that's that was that were the two
options and
and this happened over a period of one
year and this is typically how ancient
Kings of India expanded their
territories or tried to expand the
territory now understand this clearly
what sort of king would conduct what
even dare to conduct in ashram
only an extremely powerful King with the
resources at his disposal would dare to
conduct let's say I let's say I'm a king
and I have two thousand soldiers and I
have a small Kingdom and I decide that
I'm going to conduct my horse goes into
the neighboring King's territory who's
got 20 000 soldiers in a much more
territory what's gonna happen
I'm gonna be defeated and I'm gonna lose
even my territory so typically ashramas
were only conducted by very powerful
Kings other kings would not even dare to
think about it
it's only really powerful Kings would
conduct this now if you're a medical
student and if you want to do this how
many soldiers do you have at your
disposal who will obey you without
question at a second notice
you have to take these factors into
consideration do you have a horse are
you planning to buy a horse
and uh if you let your horse lose what
are the authorities the government of
India going to do about it
think about these things right it's it's
not that simple it's not just something
that you just don't want to whim it has
to be thought about very clearly and
typically what a king would do is that
maybe he would fraud the horse or induce
the horse through suggestion or whatever
to go in certain direction and in
certain things territories and so on so
this is something that very few Kings
would dare to do only those who are
genuinely powerful and they knew that
nobody could stop them only they would
do such things so we have examples of
various Vedic uh Kings who have done
this during the Rama and Mahabharata
times and you also have uh Pusha Mitra
shunga who revived the ashwameda yagna
tradition and then you also have various
Gupta emperors
who did
especially chandragupta the first I
believe and and others as well so only
very powerful Emperors not just Kings
but Emperors dare to do it so a power
hungry medical Zone it's okay to be
power hungry but you need to be
practical as well you need to First
build an army
and your army needs to have the
resources you know they need to have the
money to to feed them to give them the
weapons ammunition
then you need to build logistical routes
to to support and Supply the Army when
it is far away from your home base when
your horses are wandering around and
then you need to be able to ensure that
you will not be defeated by whoever is
in power wherever your horse goes so in
the Indians abundant the Indian
government is in power and you will not
be allowed to indulge in any such
misadventure yeah
you it won't end well for you you can
send your horse into Pakistan and see
what happens there but then are you in a
position to defeat the Pakistani army
who is not a smaller they don't have a
small Force they are pretty well
equipped especially when it comes to an
army led by a horse so think about these
things
and only when you know for sure that you
you will be able to succeed to a certain
extent only then if you think of
attempting in ashram
all right
Keisha says about Colombia and Pablo
Escobar Plata plomo right Pablo Escobar
Senor Pablo Escobar so Pablo Escobar was
well he was not the greatest drug Runner
and Drug Smuggler in history but maybe
number two the greatest drug Smuggler in
history was a Queen Victoria Empress of
India she did drug running on a scale
that Pablo Esco that makes Pablo Escobar
look like a little mosquito anyhow Pablo
Escobar was
he had this Big Cartel in Colombia he
was initially a Smuggler of various
electronics and small time things but
then he discovered cocaine I think it
was cocaine maybe some other drugs as
well and then what he started doing is
he started growing cocaine he so he
employed lots of people it was a very
well planned business business operation
you know so it's it was like it started
as a startup but then it became really
big it became a major corporation and he
would have lots of people under his
employee people would grow
uh the the plant which gives gives you
cocaine I believe coca plant yeah then
he would have
Engineers chemical Engineers Etc who
would refine the thing and distill the
cocaine out of the the pure cocaine then
he would have the entire logistical
Supply chains you know he would have uh
fleets of trucks he would have fleets of
uh even aircraft Etc and he had supply
routes going all the way into the U.S
into Miami and other places and
at one point in time he was even elected
to the
Parliament or whatever it is of Colombia
yeah and he had Ambitions of becoming
the president of Colombia and he also
did the social welfare work and he was a
you know social servant kind of thing
you know and that sort of thing So
eventually eventually he became too big
and the Americans got involved it is
eventually the Americans that took him
out yeah slowly his entire downfall
happened his uh operations were
curtailed
the Colombians with American Support
were able to slowly crack down on
various pieces of the corporation on
various Supply chains and lots of
seizures happened and so on so forth
it's a it's an interesting story
you know you can learn a lot about how
to start a business or operate a
business by looking at how the
uh cartels operate you don't I'm not
suggesting you should do anything
illegal at all but you know the way the
organization is structured how they do
things I think Patrick with David also
takes a lot of uh inspiration from the
U.S Mafia into how to run a business and
so on so yeah that's a little bit about
Colombia Colombia is a wonderful little
nation in in South America if you want
to see where it is
Colombia is here the capital is Bogota
and the cartel that Pablo Escobar ran
was based in the city of marine Medellin
or whatever you call it I'm not sure
there's there was another cartel in Kali
the Kali cartel
and uh they had I think boats or yachts
that would
transport the material to the Cayman
Islands I believe was it Cayman Islands
this there was an island called Norman's
K somewhere here that was whether it was
uh one of the Bays of operations in the
Bahamas was it I'm not sure where it was
he had a lieutenant called Carlos
leather
who used to transport a lot of this
produce into the U.S through planes so
these planes would fly very low and they
would come across Mexico and it's they
would enter the southern U.S and then
they would offload their their cargo and
that's how it made its way to the U.S
and there's a lot of U.S government
involvement in all this as well because
they also kind of you know
uh they supported certain karthills I
suppose they it is said by some
commentators that maybe they still do
even when it comes to Afghanistan the
Americans did support the
growing of opium poppies and all that
for various operations and all so yeah
it's a murky thing and there's a whole
lot of
a whole lot of stuff that you typically
don't get to see
right yeah I already answered about
Colombia Pablo Escobar what else do we
have
uh
let us see let us see what uh what other
questions do we have
um
Akshay says why didn't Indians
incorporate composite bows and other
military inventions what was it the
reason why prithviraj Chauhan lost the
battle of due to
guzni's agile archers harassing
prithvira Johan's Army
the composite bar was most likely
invented in India the double curved bow
that you see Lord Rama in depictions
using that's also invaded in India so
what's a composite bow it's a bow that's
made out of not just one piece of wood
but multiple things multiple layers and
elements of wood may be bone also all um
all engineered and fused together into a
single instrument or or weapon that's
the composite bar it's not
a standard simple bow is is made out of
a single piece of wood that you bend
through us and and you attach a rope or
cord at the end and then you pull it and
that that sort of thing composite bows
have better tensile strength and they
have multiple advantages over your
standard uh low Tech bow I think the
composite bow was used by the Mongols by
the tatars
and so on and I think most likely it was
invented in India thousands of years ago
so Indians did use it uh I'm not sure
what weapons prithviraj Chohan used in
the Second Battle of the Ryan why did
prithviraj Johan lose the Second Battle
of the ram because he won the first
battle of the Ryan and allowed
either
through commission or Omission he
allowed that guy ghazni
to escape
and because of this because he was able
to Mahmoud ghazni was able to go back to
his base in gandar in ghazni and by that
time he had already tasted the style of
warfare that the rajputs had he had been
defeated once
um I think 20th about two decades before
the first battle of the Ryan he had been
defeated somewhere in Punjab to a rajput
army later he tried to uh invade Western
India and he suffered a catastrophic
defeat to the solanki queen uh what's
her name Nike Devi in the Battle of
kayadhara in Northern Gujarat Southern
Rajasthan near Abu right and then he
again lost the first battle of the Ryan
to prithviraj Chauhan so because of all
these massive multiple defeats that he
survived he was able to understand the
rajput's tactics the Indian tactics of
how the Indians fought and eventually he
was able to find the solution to how to
deal with this and that's why
approximately one year after the first
battle of the Ryan he again
invaded India you again met with John
and this time he was able to defeat
Johan right so that's the reason why
prithvira Johan lost the first battle or
lost the Second Battle of the lion he
allowed this guy The Invader
to escape we know what happened
some people say that the the Afghans the
Invaders had better horses Nimble horses
and horses that could run faster than
the rajput horses and all that whatever
it is once you defeat your enemy you
have to ensure that enemy is crushed
forever
maybe prithvira Johan was overconfident
he said okay they are they've gone too
far and let them go whatever that should
not have happened this guy or the ghazni
was was he was injured he had to be
rescued by one of his soldiers he was
put on Horseback and then they tried to
escape and they were allowed to escape
the point is simple as a ruler as a king
you can't make excuses
this happened or that happened you have
to find a way of achieving your
objectives did not achieve his objective
maybe he didn't even think about it so
that's why
one year later lost
the Second Battle of the Rhine
okay
okay what else thousands of questions
uh some questions people are asking
repeatedly let's see something else
let's see something else
hmm
what else
Willie Bond zero zero zero zero seven
says what are you going to do with your
power is the question to build luxurious
homes for yourself or to make everyone
prosperous
good question
so think about the kings and queens the
monarchs of Europe they were very
powerful in the past 500 years let's
talk about the British Empire right the
kings and queens of England they became
very powerful because of the conquests
of in colonization of many parts of the
world including India including parts of
Africa they became very powerful they
became very wealthy as a result of all
this what did they do they built palaces
they built luxurious homes for
themselves what was the lot of the
people that they ruled the people that
they ruled were still in poverty Europe
has a feudal system please understand
this only now it has changed
Europe has a feudal system you have the
Lords you have the nobility there are
the people who serve the Lords and then
you have the peasants most people are
peasants maybe 95 of the population used
to be peasants the European aristocracy
and royalty where did it originally
derive its wealth and power from they
derived it from agricultural lands
so let's take England for instance the
crown the king of England
he was the owner of all the land in
England people who had farms and all
were actually allowed to use the farms
and do all the agriculture
on the land that was officially that of
the king
right so all the land belonged to the
king in whatever agriculture was done
the farmers The Peasants had to pay
massive taxes
to these
to the king to the to the to the crown
and then you had the various Nobles
these are people who were allowed to
have lands of their own but they were
technically again owned by the king but
they were able to they were allowed to
have their own lands employ their own
Farmers there and collect taxes from the
farmers and give some of the tax to the
to the king or queen and these Nobles
the so-called Nobles they were allowed
to have their own armies
personal armies that would that could be
called upon by the king at any time
whenever it was required so they the
deal was that they would uh
offer the arm army in the king service
and attend the mountain so that is the
original Power structure The Peasants
were the most oppressed they had almost
no rights
there was a lot of slavery for a very
long time in the in the British islands
and so on
then they colonized the world and they
enriched themselves and yet The Peasants
were always poor even a hundred years
ago or 150 in the 19th century London
was a terrible Place London was a
terrible place you have no idea about
this people used to dump human waste on
the streets in the mornings
you know and the in the aristocracy and
the nobility they used to travel in
horse drawn carriages with the windows
closed so that they don't have to get
any you know come in contact with the
common people in the dirt and the filth
yeah that's how it was
so it so what are you going to do with
your power is the question it all
depends on the system it all depends on
the king or queen when you have kings
and queens who believe that the entire
purpose of power and wealth is to serve
themselves and not the people then
you're gonna have situations like the
one that I just mentioned other on the
other hand if you have a king or a queen
that
acts on the principle that the highest
morality for them is to serve the nation
and the people and to ensure that the
nation and the people prosper in that
case when the king becomes powerful when
the nation becomes powerful it's going
to benefit the entire Society all the
people of the nation
so that's the kind of difference you see
in Egypt the kings and queens the
Pharaohs with their enormous uh
power and wealth they constructed
enormous pyramids I cannot even begin to
imagine how much money and how much time
and how much labor would have gone into
constructing these massive pyramids did
these pyramids benefit the people of
Egypt no
it did nothing for the people of Egypt
when these kings and queens of Europe
they built this enormously luxurious
palaces and castles they didn't benefit
the people no but that is all seen as
symbols of greatness
in India we had the the construction
of enormous regions of Metropolitan
regions a fully urbanized Society a
fully Urban civilization five thousand
years before today no palaces
yeah so that's the difference so it all
depends on what your values are what
your cultural values and ethics are if
you believe that the whole world is is a
resource that is to be ex that you can
extract from then you're going to have a
very uh this sort of European kind of
abrahamic kind of mindset but if you
believe that the highest Duty and
highest morality of a king is to serve
the people in the nation and ensure the
prosperity then you're going to have the
whole nation prospering and I hope that
answers the question
all right all right
says what is the minimum wavelength that
a photon can have
uh
the more energetic a photon
the shorter is wavelength
and the less energetic a photon
the longer it will look that's how it is
frequency and wavelength are
are reciprocals of each other
so when you have gamma rays the most
energetic photons you have extremely
short wavelengths when you have x-rays
which are also ionizing radiation you
have short wavelengths then a visible
light has longer wavelengths the
infrared light has even longer
wavelengths and so on so forth so what
is the minimum wavelength a photon can
have I
it would be the wavelength of the most
energetic gamma rays
so yeah that's how I would say what's
the maximum wavelength of photon could
have the maximum wavelength of photon
could have is infinity when it is
redshifted out of existence
so I don't know exactly what is the
typical wavelength of a gamma ray but
whatever it is divided by 100 and that's
possibly the most energetic gamma ray
you can have so the most energetic
photons are those that are born in the
course of stars
and the ones that were born in the very
early Universe when the universe was
still dark so one of the interesting
things that you people
ask you a question
let me ask a question if you were to if
I could give you a suit a space suit
that you can wear and it will allow you
to go right inside a star without
getting burned then what do you think
you will see if you go right to the
inside of a star
you have a star and you you're able to
go all the way inside a star to its very
core what do you think you will see
I I imagine most people think that uh
inside a star
it's just brightness right bright light
but that's not the case inside a star
it's dark
it's completely dark inside a star
you go to the core of the Sun you will
not be able to see anything it's just
Blackness Darkness it's only outside
that you will see
uh
in the atmosphere of the Sun and outside
that you see light and the the photos
that are born inside the core of the Sun
they typically take approximately a
million years to be able to escape the
Sun so the sun is so dense inside that
you have the situation
all right uh let's see some other
question uh you see I don't I don't
memorize the wavelengths and all these
things you know
so okay yeah anyway what
what other questions we have
I answered this question just some time
ago about an hour ago we don't know
what's happening there we don't know
what's happening in China maybe there's
a coup maybe some something else
happening but something clearly unusual
is happening in China
okay
Vanoss says why doesn't the government
fix our broken education system wouldn't
a good education system and interested
be good for our country and therefore
good for India's development
I have been saying this for uh for the
longest time I have two or three
episodes only about education I don't
know what is it episode 30 31 somewhere
around there yeah
the government needs to fix the
education system the education system is
the root of all India's problems
actually all the mental colonization all
the
um
all the problems that you have all the
all the false beliefs the entire
attitude of trying to memorize things
without understanding them the
inferiority complex it all comes from
India's education system so why doesn't
the government fix it because the
education system is a goddamn cartel you
know it it is something that is
the education system
it promotes mediocrity it does two
things
first of all it seeks out identifies and
destroys Talent
think about ramanujan how incredibly
talented he was but the education system
nearly destroyed him
and so it identifies seeks out and
destroys talent and secondly it promotes
mediocrity in the education system
what kind of professors are promoted
those who are great at doing politics
not those who are great at doing
research or who are very knowledgeable
it's always a political game
so the most political and most mediocre
rise to the very top that's typically
what you see in the Indian education
system
so you have a whole network of colleges
and universities all of whom are ruled
by mediocrities
not all maybe 99 maybe 98 some of the
academics and professors Etc would be
good for sure maybe one person maybe two
percent are great
but 95 98 of them are mediocre
yeah so you have a whole network the
entire system hundreds of universities
thousands of colleges all ruled with by
mediocrity right you try to reform that
don't you think there'll be resistance
to that the entire system will rebel
against you right
and and we know what what's happening
even the in the iits you have the
humanities departments that are
populated by anti-india academics
and so on so
the education system is a leftover of
the 19th century colonial system today
they will teach you computer science and
they will teach you and they will offer
you mbas but the system is the same the
system is still the same it's it's run
the same way as it was in the 19th
century you know long examinations in
which you have to write essay essay
length answers you have to memorize
things you don't you don't learn
anything at all and so on the only skill
you acquire is is how to pass exams so
this is a system it's it's like the
bureaucracy once in the if you have a
job as a professor or a lecturer or
whatever a reader in a government
college or university you have a job for
life just like the IIs
that's how it is and you try to reform
that they're going to resist
you try to reform the IIs they will all
go on strike the nation will be
paralyzed similarly you try to reform
the education system the entire system
will resist you and there's gonna be
political outcomes of that because this
system was created by the previous
political regime they benefited from
that so that's why it's so difficult for
the government to do this there are it's
gonna invite a huge amount of resistance
the media will get involved there is
that the government is going all fascist
they're they're trying to destroy what's
good and so on and and all of you will
believe this
all of you will believe what the media
says right so that's why
no matter whenever the government has
tried
to
Implement major reforms there has been a
massive backlash from political parties
from the media and all of you also most
of you believe that that the government
is doing something wrong whether it's
the farm laws whether it's agneepath and
I know I'm gonna see comments now saying
that I'm wrong so that's the problem
whenever you try to implement some good
really good major reforms there is this
massive backlash
which is orchestrated by political
parties many of which are funded by
abroad most likely not all many
and the media which again is funded by
various political parties and also by
other countries so anytime you try to
take the India the nation in the right
direction there is a major backlash
there will be protests on the streets
all the colleges and universities will
have protests Yeah by paid students or
maybe not paid students maybe they truly
believe it and so the government doesn't
want to take this up right now there are
bigger problems to solve those will be
solved first then these issues will be
taken care of when when the government
feels the time is right
the real problem is the people of India
who are so easily misled by political
parties and by the media the real
problem is that and that's why the
government doesn't want to take up such
such difficult tasks right now it makes
sense actually
here you are here you are
anyway that's fine
okay let's take some other questions
aka the guy says did the Neanderthals
have a tail and did they in Homo sapiens
coexist like a society or not
uh so the Neanderthals did not have
tails the Neanderthals were a separate
subspecies of humans
um closely related to Homo sapiens and
they
seem to have appeared in Eurasia at
least 600 000 or so years before today
Homo sapiens our ancestors they came
into Asia about 85 or 90 000 years
before today and we are the descendants
of that out of Africa migration the near
darthals where in Eurasia about half a
million years before that roughly
roughly give or take
they were very very closely related to
us they did not have Tales they had a
slightly different physique you know
they they they were more heavy heavily
built larger bones maybe more muscular
yeah
and did they and Homo sapiens coexist as
a society or not well
most non-african humans have a certain
amount of Neanderthal origin DNA
which means they did not simply coexist
they interbred
and they produced Offspring together so
a neanderthal mother or father and Homo
sapiens mother or father would procreate
together and produce an offspring that
was half Homo sapiens half Neanderthal
yeah so the typically when you have two
distinct species let's say uh
chimpanzees and gorillas they cannot
produce Offspring together because there
there is too much genetic difference
between them
whether it is a tiger and a lion I think
they can produce Offspring but The
Offspring are typically infertile or
whatever so the Neanderthals and the
humans were so genetically close
together so genetically alike that they
did interbreed they did produce
Offspring together and most non-african
humans have a little bit of Neanderthal
ancestry around four to six percent
maybe four to eight percent depending on
where you where you're looking
but from what I understand most Indians
don't have any Neanderthal ancestry
anyway that's a whole different story so
we don't know if the Neanderthals and
Homo sapiens coexisted as a society but
they did certainly meet and they did
certainly produce Offspring together and
we still see that in most non-african uh
people alive today and some of those
Neanderthal genes give us protection
give these people protection against
certain diseases and all that so it's
something that's that's been beneficial
to
humans
to homo sapiens
all right where are we
shantanu says why are we as Indians
lagging behind as far as technology is
concerned was ancient Bharat ahead in
technology than the West at that time
ancient Bharat was always
technologically the most advanced
civilization
always even in the second Millennium A.D
India was still in many ways more
advanced India was the first completely
Advanced civilization completely fully
industrialized civilization India was
the British destroyed India's Industries
because they wanted to dump their
cheaply manufactured garbage into India
and make Indians pay for that that was
one of the ways in which they extracted
wealth out of India by dumping their
cheap mass-produced textiles and other
things into India so that Indians would
buy them Indians would be forced to buy
them and they would sell them at very
high prices and that's one of the easy
ways of extracting incredible amounts of
wealth out of India
to do that they had to destroy India's
indigenous Industries and then they did
that in a variety of ways so India was
always technologically the most advanced
civilization India had the greatest ship
building industry in the world India
produced the best steel in the world and
so many other things right
so why is India lagging behind today
because we are continuing the system
that the colonizers created
the Indian system is a continuation of
the colonial system nothing has changed
after 1947.
how do you become a technologically
advanced Nation first of all you need to
have a good education system a purely
meritocratic education system secondly
you know to eliminate corruption so that
the companies and the industries and the
startups Thrive thirdly you need to make
the system uh Pro
industry
it could be really really easy to start
a business and conduct business in India
today it's not that way there's so much
red tape in this so there's been lots of
reforms in the past seven eight years
and yet we are still not where we should
be
it should be really easy to start a
business why does it even even today
take like seven days 10 days 15 days I
don't know how long it takes to even
register a business
there are certain countries in which you
can do it within one day
in India it's a whole long procedure you
to fill up so many forms and submit it
here and submit it there and you need to
hire a CA and God knows what all kinds
of things right it's a it's it's very
involved it's really hard to start a
business and then there is so much
compliance and all that stuff so it's
these are the problems
these are the problems and then when you
have a business or an industry in a
certain city you are at the mercy of the
local politicians
so there are all these issues it's the
internal problems that are that are
creating that are creating the that are
the cause of India lagging behind in
technology
today you have the government that is
involved in many of the technological
advancements we we have ISRO which is a
government-run organization this was
doing reasonably well we have drdo which
is government run organization drdo is
doing okay we have Hal Hindustan
Aeronautics limited all that
all these are government-run
organizations drdo is not well run it
has 5000 scientists and 25 000
non-scientists who are employees why
does it have 25 000 non-scientists all
the salary all the money is going into
that into into all the money
that is in on the budget of drdo for one
year a significant portion of that is
going into the salaries of the
non-scientific staff why do you need
even one non-scientific person in drdo
so that's how badly mismanaged these
things are
and why can't we have why can't we allow
private players the opportunity to
become the next drdo or ISRO or HL or
whatever so there are so many reforms
that need to be done there is a long way
to go but hopefully we are going in the
right direction this government clearly
wants to make it happen so these are the
reasons why India thus far has been
lagging behind in technology and
hopefully it will not remain this way
for too long
Madara Uchiha says even though Aryan
Invasion migration tourism picnic theory
has been proved wrong why do we still
divide our languages into Aryan and
rubidium that's what the system does
that's what the education system does
that's what Academia does I don't do it
the languages have been artificially
divided by colonizers
into these two fake artificial
categories Aryan and dravidian let's
take two languages uh Marathi and
kannada
Marathi is classified as an Aryan
language kannada is classified as a
dravidian language right
so Marathi is part of the Indo-European
language family and kannada is part of
the David and literally so if you take
Marathi and a random other Indo-European
language let's say
German
if you speak Marathi and you hear
somebody speak German how much do you
understand
zero percent if you speak Marathi and
you hear somebody speaking kannada you
will understand 30 40 of what they are
saying do you get that
and yet Marathi is part of a separate
language family and kannada is separate
this is nonsense
this is absolute nonsense
no matter which so-called dravidian
language you take it is way closer to
any of the so-called indo-aryan
languages than to any other
Indo-European language which is from
outside of India
even the indo-iranian languages which
are a larger subset of the innovarian
languages they are much closer to any of
the so-called dravidian languages than
to the European languages so this entire
classification scheme is completely
wrong it doesn't make any sense and yet
our academics
Faithfully like good Colonial slaves
keep on parroting the good old 19th
century academic Colonial Paradigm so I
have never said that we have Aryan and
David in language I said that we have to
revisit this entire thing we have to
revisit India's Linguistics a priori
from scratch
we need to uh
we need to revisit this entire thing
properly and and we need to create a new
group of linguists linguistics
researchers who are not influenced by
this nonsense but the colonial nonsense
so it needs to happen the government
needs to create a new Institute of
linguistics or Institutes of linguistics
where young researchers in their early
20s who have not been you know
contaminated by the by the slave
mindedness they will start looking at
this from scratch and create a proper
classification scheme that makes sense
logically yeah so yeah that again is
something that needs to be done and it's
something that will hope happen someday
hopefully I hope in the future
foreign
yes this is the most popular question
for today what's happening in China
right now any speculations we don't know
we don't know what's happening in China
something clearly is wrong something
very unusual is happening in China the
skies or Beijing are clear not a single
plane is taking off for landing that
never happens Beijing is one of the most
one of the busiest airports in the
entire world not only in China in the
entire world
and thousands of flights have been
canceled and thousands of trains have
also been canceled something very
strange is happening Mr XI Jin big is
not visible he's not to be seen in
public he rushed back to China after the
SEO Summit where he met Mr Putin very
stood next to Mr Modi he rushed back to
China for some reason after that he has
not been seen in public so something is
going something is going on we don't
know what it is I think time will tell
us maybe I will revisit this in
tomorrow's session if we have some more
clarity Clarity on what's Happening
how to live a life like Mikhail
Kalashnikov in India I don't know I
don't know much about
the name obviously Rings a Belling
ham
was
an engineer he was an inventor he
invented a certain weapon in 1947 which
was called the Kalashnikov 47.
47 AK-47 and then a new version of that
came out in 56
automaticov 56 ak-56 and today you have
newer versions of the Scholastic offer
series family of rifles
extremely good rifle Works in almost any
conditions very reliable very easy to
use
and that's why it's a favorite of armed
forces worldwide even terrorists and
various insurgents and Freedom Fighters
worldwide here that's how it is so yeah
um that's what I can tell you about
Mikhail karashnikov and his invention I
don't know what kind of life he lived so
I would not be able to answer that but
yeah that's what Mr Kalashnikov is
famous for
all right let's okay
I get this
uh
Aditya says Fox News anchor Tucker
Carlson tried to justify British
colonization of India that India became
civilized after the colonial rule and
the West ignored this statement
completely my thoughts
I'm not surprised at all so first the
first thing is this this guy Tucker
Carlson he's one of the prominent
right-wing voices in the U.S media right
now the U.S media is mostly left-wing
Wright is all demonized right Maga the
the Trump folks and all that the
Republicans so Tucker Carlson is one of
the prominent so supposedly right-wing
voices in the U.S
and when this old lady died what's her
name elderly lady uh the Queen the Queen
of England what's her name Elizabeth
so when she died he uh praised her to
the High Heavens he eulogized her and he
then made the statement that British
colonization was good for India without
British colonization we would not have
civilization and architecture and
whatnot
so what are my thoughts about this I'm
not surprised first of all many Indians
especially the so-called right-wing
Indians they tried to make common cause
with the right wing in the U.S and in
Europe please understand this they are
just as indophobic as anybody else they
are just as white supremacists as
anybody else these days it is not it is
not fashionable
to espouse white supremacism in in
Western Supremacy in the U.S especially
because of the kind of you know the
political climate but below the surface
that sentiment is very much there so
Tucker Carlson in these days it is not
advisable at all to make any statements
against certain religions in the West
you would be called dysphobic or that
phobic yeah and these days it is no
longer fashionable to denigrate the
people of African origin right so then
who's left
India
so it's all it's perfectly fine to be
Hindu phobic or indophobic or try to
portray India as a backward country or
whatever and nobody is going to say
anything about it heady said the same
thing
about let's say Saudi Arabia or healthy
said the same thing about some African
country there would have been a ton of
repercussions for Tucker Carlson but as
long as he does it for about India it's
perfectly fine
so my thoughts is that I am not
surprised at all and he is completely
wrong India was a civilization when the
West
well I don't want to go that far but
yeah when they were very primitive yeah
India is the oldest known civilization
on the planet
at least 10 000 years old India was
technologically and civilizationally
Incredibly highly developed even five
thousand years before today the largest
completely urbanized fully
industrialized civilization of the
ancient world
about 5000 years before today the
Sarasota Hindu phase of Indian history
which was the territorial extent was
greater than Egypt and Mesopotamia put
together it was that big it was
completely urbanized completely all
metropolitan areas very well planned
cities extremely high technology great
Hydro Engineering
and so on so I don't think there's
anything we need to prove our
architecture is it surpasses anything
the West can produce it's been doing
that for thousands of years I'm not
talking about the Monument of the of the
Invaders which is the Taj Mahal I'm
talking about all the other Monumental
architecture we have had which has been
built for public use in India all the
great temples which also served as
educational institutions and so much
more right so yeah there's nothing more
we can we need to say about this
right okay
says what if
what if Pakistan Bank Corridor emerged
in India or Pakistan Bangladesh Corridor
I think that's what Mr Gandhi wanted Mr
Mohandas Gandhi he wanted to allow the
pakistanis to create a land Corridor
land bridge between East Pakistan and
West Pakistan
to through India
the pakistanis had made this demand that
we want a land Corridor and I think Mr
Gandhi was in favor of that so imagine
if that had been allowed and they would
have had access I mean they would have
had sovereignty to Indian Territory and
then that would have well obviously not
been good for India I mean I'm glad that
better sense prevailed
and Mr Gandhi was not able to have his
way
which was Pakistan's way
so had a Pakistan Bangladesh Corridor
emerged in India it would
it would uh not have been good for India
it would have given Pakistan and the
advantage over India and of course it is
something that is completely in under
India's control obviously so was there a
war or something which did happen
eventually we would have been able to
cut it off but anyway it was not a good
idea it was a ridiculous idea and it's
strange that Mr Gandhi the great great
Indian Mahatma supported that
very strange very strange very strange
uh
yes yes it would have been a total
disaster total
okay what else do we have all kinds of
questions
one of sports says could you tell us
about the chavda dynasty
well it's one of the older and obscure
more obscure dynasties in India there
are lots of dynasties that no one writes
about or speaks about they still text
about the historical so forgotten so
this is a dynasty that uh
existed in Western India and Gujarat
Northern Gujarat Western Gujarat
in the 7th 8th centuries the oldest king
of this dynasty was
lost his kingdom to an invasion from
somewhere then his son
his wife escaped to the forests when
this Invasion happened and she gave
birth to a son about six months after
his father died this son was raised in
the forest that's why I was called one
Raj he eventually regained his father's
Kingdom and he was the one of the great
Kings of Gujarat and it is during the
rule of one Raja that Gujarat acquired a
separate uh
a socio-cultural identity it emerged as
a separate culture of its own
associations you know that sort of thing
a separate cultural identity and the
language also started changing
and this dynasty lasted until the 900s
940 to 80 or so
and the last king was childless and he
was not a very strong King and his
nephew
his sister's son
uh you served the throne and started in
a new Dynasty which is which was called
the solanki dynasty so that isn't brief
about the chapter Dynasty um it was a
reasonably strong Dynasty at some point
in time and the oldest uh ruler of this
dynasty that we can
that seems to be on the record is a
rural Coke ruler called vyakramukh
chavda who ruled in bin Mal in Rajasthan
and he seems to be to have been a honik
king he that dynasty at the time was
called the SRI chappa Dynasty later it
was called the chavda dynasty
so this King seems to have been a hornik
king who had taken the name of this
dynasty SRI chappa Dynasty and he was a
great king he was the patron of the
great uh scientist Brahma Gupta so yeah
we don't know the origins the deeper
origins of this dynasty they seem to be
linked to the skeetian king the hapana
perhaps so there isn't sufficient
evidence to either confirm or deny that
so it's it's one of the more obscure
parts of Indian history but uh it was
significant for some time and it is
during the reign of this dynasty that
Gujarat emerged as a separate uh social
cultural entity yeah
okay what else what else what else what
else uh
harsh Kumar says why are most people
right-handed while no other animals
prefer a specific arm I don't have the
answer to this
I believe polar bears are left-handed
most polar bears seem to be exclusively
left-handed
humans most of us are right-handed some
of us left-handed I don't know about
other species cats seem to be equally
Adept with both arms
so yeah I'm not quite sure I think there
must be some answer but I have not been
able to find it this far
so maybe I will revisit this but it's a
very interesting question why did we
evolve this way
we have two hands
so shouldn't we shouldn't we be able to
use both hands equally well
in some cases people also have a
preferred year and I preferred I also
like when you have to cover one eye for
shooting some people tend to only cover
one item not both eyes
like you know they prefer one eye or the
other and one year or the other I'm not
sure if it it's always the right eye the
right ear like the right hand but
interesting question and and yeah let me
try and find out why it is so so maybe
in a future episode I will look into
that
um
Oneness is Left-Handed off standings are
outstanding
I think left-handers have a certain
advantage over right-handers because the
whole world is made for right-handed so
if you are left-handed
uh it gives you some advantage in sports
and things like that you know
opposable thumbs yeah that could be a
reason but we have two opposable thumbs
so why can't we use both equally well
cats obviously don't have opposable
thumbs Bears don't have opposable thumbs
but Bears seem to be mostly left-handed
what about our cousins the chimpanzees
and gorillas do they also have this
preference for a certain hand
interesting questions and uh
I don't know the answers right now but I
will certainly look into this
all right let's see
some other questions
language classified as part of the
Iranian language family system
when even none of the words are mutually
intelligible to the Persian language I
think if Indians pay attention like
close attention to somebody speaking
Pashto we can actually make out some of
what they are saying their Pashto should
be an indo-aryan language actually but
yeah the great academicians and
linguists have placed Pashto in the
Iranian language family Hindu Iranian
language family or Iranian language so
today if you talk to people of personal
knowledge and they'll say no no we are
Persians our language is the Iranian
language blah blah blah and yet uh it's
it's there's not much of com much in
common see
there is going to be something in common
between Pashto and Iranian and Persian
just like there is a lot in common
between let's say Hindi and Persian or
Punjabi and Persian or Rajasthan in
person the languages are actually quite
close to you it's quite similar
the first time you hear the Persian
language it will sound like a foreign
alien language but if you get used to it
if you if you listen closely it starts
making a bit of sense to you persons who
come come to live in India or study in
India they pick up Hindi very very
quickly and they become fluent just like
a local almost like a local in Hindi
that's how easy it is for them to learn
Hindi because the languages are very
close
I think the Pashto language should is
actually closer to the indo-aryan
languages so-called indo-orient
languages then to the Iranian languages
but linguists have decided to put that
in that and put Pashto in that category
so yeah it doesn't make a lot of sense
to me we know that gandar was part of
ancient India and Pashto is a language
that is emerged out of gandar right the
personal people are the true in the
original inhabitants the original
natives of gandar
descendants of the
of the prithvu people and the bhakta
people those rigvedic Clans
um and genetically also Studies have
shown that the person people are
essentially essentially an extension of
the North Indian population
so yeah it doesn't make sense to for for
the Pashto language to be part of the
Iranian language family but that's where
it is right now so that's why I say that
we need to revisit the entire
categorization of classification of
Indian or subcontinental languages and
we need to revisit this and do this a
priori from from scratch
all right uh
is there any chance the Russian army
bounces back in the winter so you are
assuming that they are undergoing a
bunch of setbacks right now that's what
the media is telling us why do we have
to trust the media why do we believe the
media they have banned Russian news
outlets from social media whichever
social media platform you can think of
Russian news outlets have been banned
so the only news reports we get today
are from the Western perspective even
the India Indian news outlets there are
like two three news outlets in India two
three TV channels in India that cover
what they call geopolitics yeah they
also send their reporters to Ukraine on
Ukrainian territory or Ukrainian control
territory they have not sent a single
reporter in Russian control territory
why is this is there this lopsided
coverage this unbalanced coverage
we should see what's happening on both
sides so we are only getting news
reports from the Western perspective the
Indian media completely parrots the
Western Line
so we cannot trust what comes out of
these reports we simply can't trust it
right now they are claiming the Russians
are falling back and they they are
suffering big losses and all hey hey
let's let's see after a month or two
what the map looks like of what of who
controls what yeah let's see what it is
so uh and yeah when it comes to Winter
the Russians typically do well in winter
winter has typically historically been
Russia's Ally
whether it comes to the Napoleonic
invasion of Russia the
winter ended up destroying Napoleon's
army or whether we're talking about
Operation Barbarossa which was Hitler's
attempted invasion of Russia they the
Nazi army the vermacht reached almost at
the doorstep of Moscow but then they
paid the price of not being able to
succe not being able to succeed the
price they paid the punishment they they
suffered was the winter the Russian
winter
and the Russian army obviously knows how
to deal with its own winter so one would
expect that as the winter rolls in
Russia would have a big advantage in
whatever it is planning to do
so yes whether it is bouncing back or
going further forward Russia will most
likely do well in the
frigid Russian winter
okay AJ says depopulation is going on in
full swing across the world the last two
years future thoughts on this uh we one
does see fertility rates falling all
across Europe in the western world
and the fertility rates are way below
the replacement rate the replacement
rate of a population is when each woman
on average has 2.1 children on average
yeah and right now in the past two three
years especially after the the pandemic
we are seeing uh fertility rates
crashing very badly in Europe in the
Americas and so on in China the
fertility rate is below replacement in
Japan it is way below replacement India
is just at replacement or slightly below
now
so yeah if it continues like this you're
gonna have depopulation Long Run 100
years 200 years the world could have a
significantly smaller population
so that uh
may not be the best thing in the world
uh obviously we should not have too many
humans as well billions and billions it
may not be good for the planet it is
certainly not good for the planet it
imposes a massive uh resource crunch on
the planet which means that all the
planet's resources are now uh taken over
by just one species
a hundred years ago 99 of the non-human
biomass on the planet was wild animals
99 100 years ago wild animals today
99 of the non-human biomass is domestic
animals
sheep and cows and chickens and all that
only one person is wild animals that's
how drastically we have
destroyed the planet
so if the human population
declines
it may not be a very bad thing but uh it
may not be a very good thing either for
Nations so one needs to have some kind
of balance I think Elon Musk speaks
about this right that the depopulation
is coming it's not a good thing we need
to actually increase our population
so uh a depopulation will affect certain
Nations more than other nations and
that's going to have geopolitical
consequences Japan could cease being a
major power
in the next hundred years the fertility
rate has dropped so badly the population
is aging I'm not sure what the average
age of the average Japanese person is
must be in the late 40s
more than 45 that is terrible
so the the average the average person is
in their late 40s most likely
even when it comes to China the
population is getting older and older
now they have stopped their one child
policy but maybe it's too late and
they're gonna have a big crash of their
population and there's gonna be fewer
and fewer people who are
um
who can be part of the workforce right
so that's going to be problematic for
China now when it comes to India we are
still kind of okay
we already have a massive huge
population 1.3 something billion
close to 1.4 billion so it is important
for India to manage the population not
let it become too large but obviously we
don't want there to be a massive and
very rapid population crash as well
so yeah it's something that will have to
be managed
uh so yeah that's where we are that's
where we are and it will definitely have
a
certain geopolitical consequences
all right
yeah porus okay what is this shantanu
says can you elaborate on the history of
porus in the war between him and like
Alexander
what's your take on the statement that
Alexander was defeated by porus or
Chandra I have never seen a statement
about Alexander and Chandra so uh
so Alexander was this brutal Greek
warlord who rampaged his way west east
of Macedonia
uh he destroyed the Persian Empire he
burned the capital city of the portions
and uh yeah and then he decided to try
invading India
because he wanted to conquer the whole
world
so he came across he reached Western
India the outskirts of Western India at
that time most likely it was the Nanda
Empire that was ruling India the Nanda
Nanda Dynasty
and uh
so Alexander did destroy various
settlements along the Sindhu River the
Indus River he did a lot of atrocities
killed lots of people
he was a very bloodthirsty person he
crucified lots of people alive in in
Persia and parts of Greece and all that
you know he did a lot of atrocities so
in India also he did such things
but then he came across this Army of
this small District level Chieftain
called purushottam in Western India
and this District level purushottam this
guy he nearly defeated Alexander if you
if you
take the Greek accounts seriously you
hear that uh the Greeks tell you that
Alexander faced a tough fight but he was
able to defeat purushottam and then he
because of his magnanimity he allowed
purushottam to remain the king but as a
vasal to Alexander that's what the
Greeks tell us right
but the truth is that purus they call
him purus the porus was a very small
Chieftain one of hundreds of Chieftains
in Western India it's like a district
level administrator that's that's what
it was and he
nearly defeated Alexander if you believe
the Greek sources now the funny thing is
that not a single Indian source
speaks about Alexander not a single
Indian historian or ancient record
mentions Alexander at all even though
there are mentions of his successor
seleucus nicator
yeah
so that is strange that the Indians did
not consider Alexander important enough
to even mention him in their history
strange isn't it so we know that
Alexander possibly defeated purushottam
and then we know that his soldiers
rebelled against him because Alexander
then said that we we will go further
east and we will fight the the Nanda
Empire
and the soldiers said have you gone mad
and they rebelled against him they
mutinied against him and they forced
Alexander to retrace his path and go
back westwards to Babylon where he is
said to have died of something either
alcohol poisoning or malaria or maybe
from the wounds and injuries he suffered
during his attempted invasion of India
so that's what I can say about this uh
had he tried invading
India further east from where he was he
would have been totally annihilated
that's how powerful the Nanda Empire was
the Nanda King was not a good King
it was a very unpopular Dynasty the
Nanda Dynasty and yet they had a very
very powerful military machine
which was very rapidly defeated by
chandragupta maurya under the guidance
of Vishnu Gupta chanakya so just a
couple of decades after the defeat of
Alexander or the eviction of Alexander
from India you have his successor
seleucus coming back to reclaim
some some territory and there was a
brief war between the seleucid Empire
and the mauryan Empire so the maurians
in just less than two decades it
defeated on the Empire and created their
own Empire in India right chandragupta
maurya so most likely it was the Nanda
Empire that was in power when Alexander
tried invading not the Maury umber most
likely but there is still a little
little bit of confusion uh but we we
have to go by
the mainstream consensus that it was the
Nanda Empire not the mauryan Empire so
Alexander was defeated by porus or or
maybe he defeated porus whatever version
you want to believe but the end result
was that Alexander was forced
to retreat from India whether he won or
he lost the end result was that
Alexander was forced to retreat from
India because his soldiers were too
frightened
to move further east into the heartland
of India this simply refused to follow
his orders to obey his orders can you
believe that
so that was the story of Alexander's
disastrous attempt to invade India
which ended up costing him his life most
likely
ayush says is cricket cricket the game
of cricket also a colonial thing a
British thing uh the modern day sport of
cricket is something that emerged out of
England yeah the Baton ball thing yeah
but if you look at the story
of the childhood of Shri Krishna
there is this episode in which he is
playing a game on the banks of the
yamuna river he's playing a game of bat
and ball
and the ball falls into the river and at
that place in the river there is this
giant snake who lives there and uh
he refuses to give the ball back or
whatever and Lord Krishna goes down and
defeats him and then spares his life and
comes back with the ball right
so there is a story of Lord Krishna
playing a game of bat and ball
which is why people say that the British
the British
accidentally rediscovered in ancient
Indian game so Cricket has its Origins
most likely in India but the British
seem to have independently discovered
that game a bit three 400 years ago yeah
all right let's take
uh some other questions
yes that's that's another game that's
somewhat similar
it's uh it's a fourth game an ancient
game in India
uh
uh rithvik says India pulled out of ipef
and rcep so how will it help with the
geopolitics of India in the tense region
as geopolitics without Geo economics is
a Fool's errand so we don't know what
was the deal India has not pulled out of
the entire indo-pacific Econo economic
thing Forum Federation whatever it is
India has pulled out of one of the
pillars which is the trade pillar
so
see the ipef is a U.S creation and when
you have a multilateral organization
which has been created with by one big
Power and when you have multilateral
organization in which you have one major
power then this organization is going to
further and promote the agenda of the
biggest Nation within its umbrella
so the ipef when it comes to trade will
further the U.S agenda the Americans
don't want India to rise to high they
don't want India to become the next
China they want India to remain a middle
power not they don't want India to
become a great power and that's why I
would say that the terms of the trade
pillar of the ipf would have been most
likely something that are not very
beneficial to India
and that's why India has most likely
done the right thing and pulled out of
the trade pillar
there was something else before the Asia
Pacific indo-pacific economic for I'm
not sure what it was there there were
other trade uh
uh organizations as well in which India
did not participate so you know India
can
do geoeconomics with a variety of
Partners
we we would like to see a multi-polar
world we will we will certainly trade
with every nation that in a way that's
beneficial for us we don't have to do it
under the terms that the Americans
impose on India right so just because
India has pulled out of the trade pillar
of the ipef doesn't mean that we have we
are going to stop trading with everybody
no
we're going to keep trading with
everybody but we will do it on mutually
beneficial beneficial terms not on the
terms dictated by the superpower India
will trade with France India will trade
with Japan India will trade with
Indonesia India will trade with various
European nations India will trade with
Africa India will trade with the Middle
East India will trade with Russia India
will even trade with China to some
extent and with the Central Asian
Nations but we will do it on our terms
in a way that's mutually beneficial we
will not do it as per the dictates of
the superpower so that is the deal uh
so it may actually help India to pull
out of the trade pillar of the ipf
because if you do that then you're gonna
have to agree to certain terms and
conditions which may not be beneficial
to you but which will further the agenda
of the U.S so so overall good I don't
know what what the exact terms and
conditions are maybe that's it's not
been revealed but
I think it's a good it's a good move
all right what else
where else are we
um
okay can a coup in Russia or China
prompt the West to further disintegrate
them into smaller entities Is it
feasible well it all depends on the
outcome of the coup does the coup make
the nation stronger or does the coup
make the nation weaker
if you have a strong leader
who is taking the nation in the right
direction and he is
uh
ousted
by a group of other people and then the
new political dispensation
causes political and economic
instability in the nation then it's
going to be beneficial for the West
but if the coup results in
a stronger system a more stable system
then it's going to benefit China or
Russia so if you have a cool there are
there are rumors of a coup going on
going around right now about a coup in
China possibly I don't know so if there
is indeed a coup and if that coup
results in a stronger China then it's
going to be bad for the west but if that
coup is going to sow chaos in China and
and create instability it will be a
great opportunity for the U.S to
possibly undermine China possibly even
disintegrated similarly for Russia Mr
Putin is a strong man he has absolute
control over Russia if there is a coup
and uh a weaker leader comes to power or
a coalition of weaker leaders that will
be a dream come true for the U.S but if
there is a coup and somebody even
stronger comes to power it's going to be
a nightmare for the US so it depends on
what happens what sort of Kuwait is and
what is the outcome of the coup yeah
so in case the coup creates instability
and Chaos it is certainly feasible for
the West to take advantage of that and
disintegrate the nation into smaller
entities
yeah that's how it goes
right where else what else
is it cool or is it Cooper
the word c-o-u-p-q is a French word so
in French you say coup you don't say
coop
but yeah if you were to go with the
British pronunciation it should be coup
but many of these words in the English
language they come from the French
language and uh yeah so that's why we
say
right
um
okay any other question
should India also disintegrate other
nations well there are two Nations that
need to be reconfigured in the long run
first of all Pakistan needs to cease to
exist as in the in the shape and form it
is today we need to ensure that Pakistan
the various regions of Pakistan go their
separate way ways
region and the Northwest Frontier
province
shall we look at the map where's the map
here's the map
in the
the all the in the Northwest Frontier
province that should mostly go back into
Afghanistan because that's what the
pashtoons seek and I think that is a
valid justify of justifiable demand
Balochistan should be free sin there
should be free and the Pakistani portion
of Punjab should also be independent for
some time and obviously uh Pakistan
occupied Jammu and Kashmir all of that
should come back into India so yes India
showed disintegrate Pakistan I do not
wish any harm to the people of Pakistan
who are our brothers and sisters they
are same blood as our same origin same
history same ancestry but I we do need
to uh reconfigure the map of Pakistan
and ensure that Pakistan ceases to exist
as a nation because it has been it is an
artificial and temporary Nation I
haven't said that today right temporary
Nation here we go so Pakistan is an
artificial and temporary nation that was
created by outside forces to harm India
and to further those outside forces
geopolitical interests it doesn't suit
the interests of the people of this
Indian subcontinent that's why we need
to reconfigure Pakistan disintegrated
yes and ensure that the people of the
region have a better life and a better
future similarly we need to
in the long run ensure that Tibet
becomes independent again India does not
seek to rule Tibet Tibet should be an
independent nation again that is the
only solution to the India China border
dispute China has no business being in
Tibet as long as China occupies Tibet
India and China will have very tense and
very adversarial relations that is
unnatural India and China have always
been the best of friends for 2000 years
ever since India civilized China right
so in the long run India needs to ensure
that Tibet regains its independence
which would mean disintegrating China in
the shape and form that it is today
so that is the answer to your question
India needs to disintegrate Pakistan and
also India needs to
free Tibet from China it's not an easy
task it's not that's something that's
going to happen next weekend or next
year but in the next 20 years these
things need to happen
for India
and the people of the subcontinent to
have a better future and also for the
people of Tibet the Chinese people can
go their way they have no business being
in China so yes that's what needs to
happen
shall we take one more question
all right
yeah I don't even know what
what decoloniality is yeah I haven't
read those books these days which are
quite popular
uh Bobby says also creates a buffer and
Tibet was longing for Independence since
occupation I could not agree more yes so
if you have a free Tibet
it will be great for the people of Tibet
they'll finally be free from nearly a
century of foreign occupation it will be
great for that it will also create a
buffer between India and China so if
India becomes too powerful it will be a
good thing for China that there's a huge
landmass that separates China from India
again
if Tibet is free and if China becomes
very powerful it's a good thing for
India because it's a big land mass which
is independent it's a buffer between
India and China so it is good for both
Nations for India as well as China so
yes that's what needs to happen and
that's what India and story engineer the
Chinese will not allow that the Chinese
will not be in favor of that but India
needs to do that
China cool flights canceled yes I just
showed it to you on the uh on the flight
radar uh website you can see that the
flights Lots thousands of flights have
been canceled
are you ritual
and
I'm not sure what that means am I ritual
I'm I'm a human being I'm sure you meant
something I could not get it I apologize
but uh
okay Shaheen says what do you think
about India's three historical blunders
as described by by our minister of
external Affairs Dr s Jai Shankar is
there any other blender you want to add
what are the blunders the three he did
say something one was partition one was
um
keeping the West at arm's length and
third was I'm not sure what it was not
uh the lack of economic growth was it
I'm not sure
uh one of the yeah partition obviously
the allowing the creation of Pakistan
was indeed a blunder
it was indeed a blunder yes
um allowing someone like Mr nehru to be
appointed and selected the Prime
Minister was obviously a blunder because
that's why all many of these things
happened allowing the Chinese to take
over Akshay chin and the government was
sleeping about it for five years they
were not even aware of it that's an
incredible blunder incredible blunder
you know what happened here here's what
happened
you have this region over here uh these
days Google is playing nice but this
region aksai chin this big region over
here is currently under illegal Chinese
occupation so what happened in the early
1950s is that the Chinese started
constructing a road in this region and
they de facto annexed this entire
enormous region and the Indian
government was not even aware of it and
when Mr nehru was told about it he said
what's the problem what's the big deal
not even a blade of grass glows there
grows there so yeah that's a major
blunder and what other blunders do we
have not allowing the Air Force to take
part in the 1962 War
if the Air Force had participated in the
in the 1960 War the result could have
been different or maybe not but at least
it would have been a better result for
India yeah so Mr nehru did not allow the
Air Force to operate in the 1962 War
which is incredibly strange I mean who
was supporting India or China makes one
Wonder obviously he's a magnificent
person and a great person but yes we are
we have smaller people so we should
still think about it right
and so on and allowing Pakistan to take
over a poke Pakistan
not allowing the Indian army to
recapture Pok and gilgit baltistan that
is an incredible blunder
Mr Nero said no we'll not go go further
the Army should stop and we will go to
the U.N
why
anyway there are so many such blunders
but just a few of them I can I can speak
about right now
okay
I'll take one more question
one more question
what do we have
are we trying to decipher the IVC script
the Indus Valley Civilization script are
always still waiting for for westerners
I think we have reached the stage where
individuals can use
can use scientific techniques to this to
decipher the script there is a person
called yajna devam that's the online
handle they seem he or she seems to have
deciphered the script I keep saying that
I'm going to study it I still don't have
the time but it looks like a
decipherment has been done it looks like
it is Vedic Sanskrit
anyway that that needs to be obviously
corroborated independently but yeah we
are we have individuals within India not
in the academic system which is hopeless
but we have individuals independent
people who are trying to decipher it and
there seems to be extremely good
progress happening in that direction so
let's not wait for anybody we should do
it ourselves
tell us about one of the most powerful
Kings founder of the Nanda Dynasty so
mahaprada was
I don't know what his uh ancestry was
either he was the son of the last king
of the previous Dynasty
or he was the son of a barber or
whatever but he was able to uh establish
his own Dynasty the Nanda Dynasty he
became very powerful in a very short
period of time he was a very unpopular
King
he had very unpopular policies he uh
used to Levy very oppressive taxes on
the people and he was a very very
ruthless collector of taxes he enriched
himself with the expense of the Empire
and the people a king or an emperor when
they when they Levy taxes those taxes
need to be reinvested in infrastructure
and in in ensuring the prosperity of the
nation and the people it is the tax is
supposed to serve the nation in the case
of mahapatnam he amassed it to enrich
himself so the nation was suffering
the people are unhappy but he was very
powerful he had a very powerful Army and
in a very short period of time he was
able to consolidate his power on very
very large parts of India it is uh yeah
and then he had a number of successors
who were all weaker and weaker and
eventually we know that uh the dynasty
was supplanted by the mauryan dynasty
of whom Chandra Gupta Mori was the first
emperor anyhow that's the answer and uh
yeah that's it for tonight thank you
very much everybody for all the
questions uh very interesting times we
are living in may you live in
interesting times that's what they say
as a curse but anyhow that's why that's
where we are so thank you for the
questions very interesting session as
always and I will see you
in tomorrow's session which will be
mainly about geopolitics and history and
current affairs I will see you then in
24 or so hours until then take care good
night good day I'll see you soon bye